"lang"
{
"Language" "thai"
"Tokens"
{
"lostcoast.fish_bequick"		"เร็วเข้าเถอะไอ้น้อง ไม่งั้นคงไม่เหลืออะไรแน่"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_bequick"		"We'd better be quick, lad, or there'll be nothing left to save."
"lostcoast.fish_beyondrocks"		"ไปเร็วเข้า ประตูอยู่ถัดจากหินนั่น"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_beyondrocks"		"Let's hurry on, then.  The gate's just beyond those rocks."
"lostcoast.fish_bullsquidtrap"		"รอก่อน..เราต้องยกแผงปิดอันนี้ขึ้น เราเคยดักตัวบูลสควิดได้ที่นี่"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_bullsquidtrap"		"Hold up now...we've got to raise this hatch.  We used to trap bullsquid in here."
"lostcoast.fish_cantprance"		"ฉันไม่สามารถข้ามหินนั่นไปได้เหมือนแต่ก่อนแล้ว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cantprance"		"Can't prance over these rocks like I used to."
"lostcoast.fish_canyouhearme"		"ได้ยินฉันไหม?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_canyouhearme"		"Can you hear me?"
"lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb01"		"ระวังหน่อย พ่อหนุ่ม"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb01"		"Watch your step up there, laddy!"
"lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb02"		"อย่ามองลงไป!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb02"		"Don't look down!"
"lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb03"		"ทำได้ดีแล้วน้องชาย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cliffclimb03"		"You're doin fine, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_cometostolga"		"ไป St. Olga กับฉัน!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cometostolga"		"Come on with me to St. Olga!"
"lostcoast.fish_cough01"		"[เสียงไอกระแอม]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cough01"		"[Coughing, Throat clearing]"
"lostcoast.fish_cough02"		"[เสียงไอกระแอม]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cough02"		"[Coughing, Throat clearing]"
"lostcoast.fish_cough03"		"[เสียงไอกระแอม]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cough03"		"[Coughing, Throat clearing]"
"lostcoast.fish_cough04"		"[เสียงไอกระแอม]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_cough04"		"[Coughing, Throat clearing]"
"lostcoast.fish_crabpot01"		"ไม่มีอะไรเศร้าไปกว่าไม่มีปูในที่ดักสักตัวเดียว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_crabpot01"		"Nothing sadder than an empty crab pot."
"lostcoast.fish_crabpot02"		"พวกปลิงกินปูไปเกือบหมด"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_crabpot02"		"Leeches ate most of the crabs."
"lostcoast.fish_crabpot03"		"อย่าลืมเอามันกลับไปไว้ที่เดิมด้วยล่ะ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_crabpot03"		"Be sure to put that back where you found it."
"lostcoast.fish_crabpot04"		"หยุดง่วนกับการหาเถอะ เราได้ปลาตัวโตมาทอดแล้ว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_crabpot04"		"Stop messing around.  We got bigger fish to fry."
"lostcoast.fish_destroygun"		"ไปเร็วเข้าพ่อหนุ่ม ทำลายปืนนั่น อย่าชักช้า"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_destroygun"		"Get along, now, laddy.  Destroy that gun, and no dawdling."
"lostcoast.fish_feast"		"เราจะฉลองชัยชนะกันอย่างอิ่มหนำ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_feast"		"We'll celebrate this victory with a feast!"
"lostcoast.fish_fishman01"		"เดี๋ยวนะ...คุณไม่ใช่....?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_fishman01"		"Wait a minute now...aren't you....?"
"lostcoast.fish_fishman02"		"ใช่แน่! คุณคือนักวิทยาศาสตร์ Friedman, Fishman ใช่ไหม?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_fishman02"		"You are!  You're that scientist chap-Friedman, Fishman-am I right?"
"lostcoast.fish_followmelad"		"ตามฉันมาสิพ่อหนุ่ม"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_followmelad"		"Follow me, lad."
"lostcoast.fish_getgoing"		"รีบหน่อย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_getgoing"		"Get going!"
"lostcoast.fish_gettingfuzzy"		"คุณกำลังหายตัวไปแถวมุมนั่น"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_gettingfuzzy"		"You're getting fuzzy around the edges!"
"lostcoast.fish_gettoshelter"		"เราไปเข้าที่กำบังเถอะ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_gettoshelter"		"Let's get you to shelter!"
"lostcoast.fish_getup"		"ลุกขึ้นไอ้หนู เราต้องไปจากที่นี่!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_getup"		"Get up, lad, we've got to get out of here!"
"lostcoast.fish_getuppath"		"เร็วเข้าน้องชาย! ไปตามทางนั่น!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_getuppath"		"Hurry, lad!  Get up the path!"
"lostcoast.fish_gothru"		"เข้าไปเลยไอ้น้อง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_gothru"		"Go on through, lad."
"lostcoast.fish_grieve01"		"โถ ไม่น่าเลย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_grieve01"		"Well, ain't that shame?"
"lostcoast.fish_grieve02"		"ฉันน่าจะออกไปเอง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_grieve02"		"Guess I'd better be heading out."
"lostcoast.fish_grieve03"		"โอไอ้หนุ่ม...คิดว่าวันนี้ยังไม่ใช่วันของนายแล้วกัน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_grieve03"		"Well, laddy...guess this just wasn't your day."
"lostcoast.fish_guide01"		"ตามมาทางนี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide01"		"Come on, then."
"lostcoast.fish_guide02"		"ไปกันเลย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide02"		"Here we go."
"lostcoast.fish_guide03"		"ทางนี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide03"		"This way now."
"lostcoast.fish_guide04"		"เดินระวังด้วย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide04"		"Watch your step."
"lostcoast.fish_guide05"		"ค่อยๆ ก้าวไอ้น้อง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide05"		"Step lightly there, laddy."
"lostcoast.fish_guide06"		"ง่ายขึ้นแล้ว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide06"		"Easy now."
"lostcoast.fish_guide07"		"ไปได้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_guide07"		"There you go."
"lostcoast.fish_headingout"		"ทุกคนมุ่งหน้าออกไปกันแล้ว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_headingout"		"Everyone's heading out."
"lostcoast.fish_hearthat"		"ได้ยินเสียงนั่นไหม"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hearthat"		"Did you hear that?"
"lostcoast.fish_hey"		"เฮ้!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hey"		"Hey!"
"lostcoast.fish_holdon"		"ระวัง!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_holdon"		"Hold on!"
"lostcoast.fish_holymother"		"โอ พระองค์ St. Olga"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_holymother"		"Holy Mother of...St. Olga."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_good"		"ดี"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_good"		"Good."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt01"		"[เสียงหายใจเหนื่อยหอบ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt01"		"[Huffing and puffing sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt02"		"[เสียงหายใจเหนื่อยหอบ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt02"		"[Huffing and puffing sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt03"		"[เสียงหายใจเหนื่อยหอบ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt03"		"[Huffing and puffing sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt04"		"[เสียงหายใจเหนื่อยหอบ] ฉันคงแก่เกินไปกับงานพรรค์นี้..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_grunt04"		"[Huffing and puffing sounds] I'm gettin' too old for this kinda nonsense..."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_keeppulling"		"นั่นแหละ ดึงต่อไปเรื่อยๆ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_keeppulling"		"That's it.  Keep pulling."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_keepup"		"อย่าหยุดนะไอ้น้อง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_keepup"		"Keep up with me, laddy."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_nag01"		"ต่อไป หยิบตะขออีกอัน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_nag01"		"Go on, now, pick up the other hook."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_nag02"		"หยิบตะขออีกอัน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_nag02"		"Grab other hook."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_nicework"		"เยี่ยมมาก!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_nicework"		"Nice work!"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_nowpull"		"ได้แล้วไอ้น้อง เอ้า...ดึงเลย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_nowpull"		"Fine, laddy.  Now...pull."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_sigh01"		"[ถอนหายใจขณะเขาต้องต้านน้ำหนักที่แสนหนักหน่วง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_sigh01"		"[Sigh of relief as he slips off the strenuous weight]"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_sigh02"		"[ถอนหายใจขณะเขาต้องต้านน้ำหนักที่แสนหนักหน่วง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_sigh02"		"[Sigh of relief as he slips off the strenuous weight]"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_slipover"		"เกี่ยวที่ตะขออันใหญ่นั่น"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_slipover"		"Slip it over the big hook, laddy."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_take"		"เอาล่ะ ฉันจะจับตะขอนี่ นายจับอีกอันตรงโน้น"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_take"		"Here now, I'll grab this hook, you take hold of that other one there."
"lostcoast.fish_hook_thatsit"		"นั่นแหละ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_thatsit"		"That's it!"
"lostcoast.fish_hook_thereyougo"		"ไปได้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hook_thereyougo"		"There you go."
"lostcoast.fish_hurryuplad"		"เร็วหน่อยพ่อหนุ่ม!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_hurryuplad"		"Hurry up, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_illbehere"		"ถ้าคุณทำสำเร็จกลับมาอย่างปลอดภัย ฉันจะรอคุณที่นี่"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_illbehere"		"If you make it back safely, I'll be here waiting for you."
"lostcoast.fish_infernalleeches"		"ปลิงดูดเลือดพวกนี้จะกร่อนกระดูกนายหายไปเพียงพริบตาเดียวเลยล่ะ และฉันไม่สนใจหรอกว่านายจะใส่ชุดว่ายน้ำที่หรูขนาดไหน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_infernalleeches"		"These infernal leeches'll clean your bones in a trice, and I don't care what kinda fancy swimsuit you're wearing!"
"lostcoast.fish_keepclose"		"ทีนี้ก็เดินตามมาใกล้ๆ ฉัน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_keepclose"		"Here, now, keep close to me."
"lostcoast.fish_key_ahno"		"อ้ากก! ... ไม่..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_ahno"		"Ah!  ...  No..."
"lostcoast.fish_key_gotrighthere"		"กุญแจน่าจะอยู่ที่ใดที่หนึ่ง...แถวนี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_gotrighthere"		"Got the key right here...somewhere..."
"lostcoast.fish_key_notit"		"ไม่ใช่อันนี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_notit"		"That's not it."
"lostcoast.fish_key_notneither"		"ไม่ นี่ก็ไม่ใช่อีก"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_notneither"		"No, that's not it neither."
"lostcoast.fish_key_notthatone"		"อืมม อันนั่นก็ไม่ใช่"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_notthatone"		"Hm.  Not that one."
"lostcoast.fish_key_therewego"		"ได้แล้วไปเถอะ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_key_therewego"		"There we go."
"lostcoast.fish_likeleeches"		"ฉัน..เอ่อ..หวังว่าคุณคงชอบปลิงนี่"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_likeleeches"		"I, eh, hope you like leeches."
"lostcoast.fish_lookoutbelow"		"ระวังข้างล่างด้วย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_lookoutbelow"		"Look out below!"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble01"		"<เสียงพูดตะกุกตะกักฟังไม่ได้สรรพ>"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble01"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble02"		"ไอ้บ้าเอ๊ย แกคงไม่รู้ว่า....."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble02"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble03"		"หากคิดว่าเขารู้ทุกเรื่อง ฉันคิดว่านะ..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble03"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble04"		"ฉันต้องถามตัวเองว่า ทำไมฉันยังอยู่ในดินแดนโหดร้ายเช่นนี้ กินโคลนก็ไม่ได้ มิหนำซ้ำจะโดนปลิงกินคุณก่อน อันตรายเหลือเกิน..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble04"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble05"		"มีเพียงสิ่งเดียว- ฉันมีชีวิตอยู่มานานเพื่อทำในสิ่งต่างๆ-และตอนนี้พวกมันกำลังเอาทุกสิ่งจากฉันไป..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble05"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_mumble06"		"ฉันคิดถึงเธอ... ฉันควรฟังคำเตือนของแม่ ฉันจำไม่ได้ว่าแม่พูดอะไร แต่ฉันควรฟังคำของแม่ ฉันรู้ดี..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_mumble06"		"[Various mumblings]"
"lostcoast.fish_myback"		"โอยย! หลังฉันแย่ล่ะ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_myback"		"Oomph!  There goes my back."
"lostcoast.fish_niceknowingya"		"ดีใจที่รู้จักนาย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_niceknowingya"		"Nice knowing ya!"
"lostcoast.fish_oldleg"		"ขาฉันมีปัญหาแน่ๆ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_oldleg"		"This old leg's been giving me trouble."
"lostcoast.fish_ontherock"		"อยู่บนเขาโน่นไง โบสถ์ St. Olga."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_ontherock"		"That's her on the rock, up there.  Church of St. Olga."
"lostcoast.fish_otherplaces"		"อืมม...ฉันเดาว่าคุณคงมีที่อื่นแล้ว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_otherplaces"		"Well...I guess you've got other places to be."
"lostcoast.fish_outofbreath01"		"[เสียงหายใจหอบฮั่กๆ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_outofbreath01"		"[Breathless panting sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_outofbreath02"		"[เสียงหายใจหอบฮั่กๆ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_outofbreath02"		"[Breathless panting sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_outofbreath03"		"[เสียงหายใจหอบฮั่กๆ]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_outofbreath03"		"[Breathless panting sounds]"
"lostcoast.fish_path"		"มีเส้นทางใต้หน้าผา ฉันจะพาคุณไปที่ประตู และหลังจากนั้น....ก็ขึ้นอยู่กับคุณ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_path"		"There's a path at the bottom of the cliff.  I'll let you through the gate, and then...well, the rest is up to you."
"lostcoast.fish_pathupcliff"		"มีเส้นทางเหนือหน้าผานั่น ต้องเดินอย่างระวัง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_pathupcliff"		"There's a path up the cliff.  Step lightly now."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk01"		"อืมม ก็อย่างที่ฉันพูดนั่นแหละ..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk01"		"Well, as I was saying..."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk02"		"อย่างที่ฉันพูดใช่ไหม โอ ใช่เลย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk02"		"What was I saying?  Oh yeah."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk03"		"ตอนนี้ ฉันอยู่ที่..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk03"		"Now, where was I..."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk04"		"อืมม ไม่ว่ายังไง..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk04"		"Hm.  Anyway..."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk05"		"อืมม นั่นไงอย่างที่ฉันพูดเลย..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk05"		"Well, now, as I was saying..."
"lostcoast.fish_resumetalk06"		"อืมม ก็อย่างที่ฉันพูดนั่นแหละ..."
"[english]lostcoast.fish_resumetalk06"		"Well, as I was saying before..."
"lostcoast.fish_shellingbeach"		"รีบไปก่อนจะโดนระดมยิงบนหาดนี้!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_shellingbeach"		"They'll be shelling this beach before long!"
"lostcoast.fish_shootgull01"		"เฮ้! เราสูญเสียสัตว์โลกไปมากพอแล้ว!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_shootgull01"		"Hey, now!  We've lost enough species already!"
"lostcoast.fish_shootgull02"		"นกนางนวลนั่นทำอะไรให้คุณเหรอ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_shootgull02"		"What'd that gull ever do to you?"
"lostcoast.fish_shootgull03"		"อย่ายิงนกนางนวล! พวกมันช่วยลดจำนวนปลิงได้มาก!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_shootgull03"		"Don't shoot the gulls!  They keep down the leech population!"
"lostcoast.fish_shootgull04"		"สมกับคุณดีนะ ฉันไม่หยุดคุณหรอก"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_shootgull04"		"Well, suit yourself.  I can't stop you."
"lostcoast.fish_slowdown"		"ช้าลงหน่อยน้องชาย"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_slowdown"		"Slow down, wouldja?"
"lostcoast.fish_stayclosetome"		"อยู่ใกล้ๆ ฉันไว้ น้องชาย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_stayclosetome"		"Stay close to me now."
"lostcoast.fish_stayoutwater"		"ไม่ว่าคุณจะทำอะไร อยู่ห่างจากน้ำไว้ดีกว่า"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_stayoutwater"		"Whatever you do, stay out of the water."
"lostcoast.fish_strand"		"เห็นคุณนอนเกยหาดอยู่ที่นี่ ขณะที่ฉันกำลังไปที่อ่าว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_strand"		"Saw you lying on the strand over here, as I was heading into the bay."
"lostcoast.fish_takeoncombine"		"คุณต้องมาที่นี่เพื่อกำจัดพวก Combine แน่ๆ ฉันก็ไม่แน่ใจนักว่าชายคนเดียวจะทำอะไรได้ แต่...คงไม่มีเหตุผลอื่นที่มา St. Olga ในช่วงเวลานี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_takeoncombine"		"You must be here to take on the Combine.  Not sure what one man can do, but...no other reason to visit St. Olga at a time like this."
"lostcoast.fish_takeoutgun"		"คุณเอาปืนนั่นไป และคนที่ St. Olga จะให้การต้อนรับคุณแม้ว่าจะไม่รู้จัก"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_takeoutgun"		"You take out that gun, and the people of St. Olga will give you such a welcome as you've never known."
"lostcoast.fish_taketobase"		"ฉันจะพาคุณไปที่ฐานของพวกเขา หรือไปไกลเท่าที่ฉันจะไปถึง"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_taketobase"		"I'll take you where they made their base-or as far as I can, at any rate."
"lostcoast.fish_takeyouthere"		"ฉันจะพาคุณไปที่นั่น ให้ไกลที่สุดเท่าที่จะทำได้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_takeyouthere"		"I'll take you there, lad.  Or as far as I can, at any rate."
"lostcoast.fish_theresgate"		"นั่นไงประตู"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_theresgate"		"Ah, here's the gate."
"lostcoast.fish_tooclose"		"ไม่อยากเจอใกล้ๆ งี้เลย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_tooclose"		"Little too close for comfort!"
"lostcoast.fish_unlockgateforya"		"ฉันจะปลดล็อคประตูนี่ให้คุณ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_unlockgateforya"		"Here, now, let me just unlock this gate for ya."
"lostcoast.fish_wait01"		"มีอะไรเฝ้าดูคุณอยู่?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wait01"		"What's keeping you?"
"lostcoast.fish_wait02"		"มาทางนี้เถอะ"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wait02"		"Come along now."
"lostcoast.fish_wait03"		"มาตามทางเลยพ่อหนุ่ม!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wait03"		"Pick up the pace, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_wait04"		"ทางนี้ไอ้หนุ่ม!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wait04"		"This way, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_waitforme"		"รอฉันด้วย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waitforme"		"Wait for me!"
"lostcoast.fish_waitup"		"รอก่อนไอ้น้อง!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waitup"		"Wait up, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_warmingupgun"		"พวกมันกำลังเตรียมปืนแล้วไอ้น้อง นี่คือสิ่งที่ฉันกลัว"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_warmingupgun"		"They're warming up the gun, lad.  I'm afraid this is it."
"lostcoast.fish_watchitupthere"		"ดูนี่สิ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_watchitupthere"		"Watch it up there!"
"lostcoast.fish_watchstep"		"เดินระวังๆ หน่อยพ่อหนุ่ม"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_watchstep"		"Watch your step there, lad."
"lostcoast.fish_waterwarn01"		"ออกมาจากแอ่งน้ำ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waterwarn01"		"Get out of the water!"
"lostcoast.fish_waterwarn02"		"อยู่ห่างจากน้ำไว้!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waterwarn02"		"Stay clear of the water!"
"lostcoast.fish_waterwarn03"		"คุณไม่ได้มีปลิงอยู่มากพอแล้วรึ?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waterwarn03"		"Haven't you had enough of them leeches?"
"lostcoast.fish_waterwarn04"		"ปลิงจะดูดเลือดคุณทันทีที่มันเห็นคุณ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_waterwarn04"		"The leeches'll eat you soon as look at you!"
"lostcoast.fish_wheretheyare"		"นั่นคือที่ที่พวกเขาอยู่ โบสถ์ St. Olga"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wheretheyare"		"That's where they are, up there.  Church of St. Olga."
"lostcoast.fish_whereyagoing"		"เฮ้ คุณจะไปไหน?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whereyagoing"		"Hey, where ya going?"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling01"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling01"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling02"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling02"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling03"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling03"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling04"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling04"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling05"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling05"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_whistling06"		"[เสียงผิวปากและฮัมเพลง]"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_whistling06"		"[Whistling and humming]"
"lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown01"		"Combine ปรากฏตัวเมื่อวาน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown01"		"Combine showed up yesterday."
"lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown02"		"เช้านี้พวกมันกระหน่ำยิงจนกระสุนหมด"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown02"		"By this morning they were firing off empty shells."
"lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown03"		"เหมือนมันต้องการถล่มทั้งเมืองให้ราบ เพื่อทำเป็นฐานทัพของพวกมัน"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_wipeouttown03"		"Looks like they're planning to wipe out the town so they can have the whole place for a base."
"lostcoast.fish_youalive"		"คุณยังไม่ตาย!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_youalive"		"You're alive!"
"lostcoast.fish_youallright"		"ไม่เป็นไรใช่ไหม?"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_youallright"		"Are you all right?"
"lostcoast.fish_youdidit"		"สำเร็จแล้ว!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_youdidit"		"You did it, lad!"
"lostcoast.fish_youthere"		"คุณตรงนั้นน่ะ!"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_youthere"		"You there!"
"lostcoast.fish_zombiegun"		"คุณต้องมานี่เพื่อกำจัดไอ้ซอมบี้แน่ๆ คงไม่มีเหตุผลอื่นที่จะมา St. Olga ในช่วงเวลานี้"
"[english]lostcoast.fish_zombiegun"		"You must be here to destroy the zombie gun.  No other reason to visit St. Olga at a time like this."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_beach.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] ตอนที่ฝ่ายศิลป์เริ่มคิดเกี่ยวกับสถานที่ที่จะใช้แสดงความโดดเด่นของ HDR ชายหาดเป็นตัวเลือกแรกที่เราเลือก ความสัมพันธ์ของภาพระหว่างท้องฟ้า น้ำ และก้อนหิน เป็นสิ่งที่เราคงไม่สามารถไปถึงได้ถ้าไม่มี HDR เพื่อให้ High Dynamic Range จำลองผลของแสงที่มีต่อพื้นผิวรอบตัวคุณอย่างถูกต้อง เช่น ก้อนหินเปียกๆ พวกนี้ เราจะต้องใช้ข้อมูลเกี่ยวกับพื้นผิวที่ละเอียดมากกว่าที่เราเคยใช้ ในตอนนี้ เรากำลังสร้างโมเดลเท็กซ์เจอร์แบบ 3D เพื่อให้ได้ข้อมูลทางกายภาพที่เข้ารหัสในเท็กซ์เจอร์ ซึ่งช่วยให้ HDR สามารถสะท้อนแสงออกจากพื้นผิวได้อย่างถูกต้อง และเรายังออกแบบสีและค่าสำหรับแต่ละพื้นผิวเพื่อให้พื้นผิวเหล่านั้นแสดงผลอย่างถูกต้องในทุกระดับแสง"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_beach.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] When the art team started to think about a location that would demonstrate the power of HDR, a beach was one of the first choices we made. The visual relationship between the sky, the water, and the rocks is something we could not achieve without HDR. In order for high dynamic range to correctly simulate the light's interaction with the surfaces around you, like these wet rocks, we needed more precise information about the surfaces than we've had in the past. So now, going forward, we're modelling textures in 3D packages to ensure that the physical information encoded in the texture allows HDR to correctly bounce light off the surface. We also design the colors and values of each surface to ensure they will be correct across all exposure levels."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_character.wav"		"[Randy Lundeen] กระบวนการในการสร้างตัวละครใน Half-Life 2 ได้สอนพวกเราหลายอย่าง ในที่สุดแล้ว เราเชื่อว่าเราได้ค้นพบกระบวนการที่มีประสิทธิภาพมากขึ้นสำหรับการออกแบบและสร้างตัวละคร ชาวประมงคนนี้เป็นตัวละครแรกที่เราสร้างด้วยกระบวนการดังกล่าว ในด้านการออกแบบ ชาวประมงถูกสร้างขึ้นเพื่อใช้ในการแสดง HDR และลักษณะของแสงที่ตกลงบนผิวคน ไฮไลต์บริเวณหน้าผากและจมูกเป็นตัวอย่างที่ดีสำหรับความมันวาวของผิวคน คุณสามารถเห็นรอยย่นที่แก้ม และรอบๆ ดวงตา ซึ่งเป็นตัวอย่างของวิธีที่เราใช้ Normal map เพื่อเพิ่มความลึก ในด้านการผลิต ชาวประมงถูกสร้างโดยใช้กระบวนการที่คล้ายกับที่ใช้สร้างก้อนหินที่คุณเห็นบนชายหาด เราสร้างโมเดลตัวละคร 3D ที่มีรายละเอียดสูงมาก จากนั้นแยกข้อมูลทางกายภาพออกมาและเก็บไว้ในเท็กซ์เจอร์"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_character.wav"		"[Randy Lundeen] The process of building characters in Half-Life 2 taught us many things. By the end, we believed we'd figured out a more effective process for designing and constructing characters. This fisherman is the first character we've built using that process. Design-wise, the fisherman was focused on showcasing HDR, and the way light falls on human skin. The highlights on his forehead and nose are good examples of specularity on human skin. You can see how the wrinkles on his cheeks, and around his eyes, are an example of how we can use normal maps to add depth. Production-wise, the fisherman was built using a similar process to the rocks you saw on the beach. We model the 3D character at a very high detail, then extract much of the physical information and store it in the textures."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_cliffside.wav"		"[Robin Walker] พื้นที่ซึ่งคุณกำลังเข้าไปเรียกว่าคลิฟไซด์อารีน่า พวกเราชื่นชอบเป็นพิเศษกับหน้าผาแนวดิ่งใน Half-Life 1 และรู้สึกเสียดายที่เราไม่ได้ใช้แนวคิดนั้นอีกใน Half-Life 2 พื้นที่แนวตั้งช่วยให้เราสามารถบังคับให้ผู้เล่นต้องจัดการกับการโจมตีจากทางด้านบนและด้านล่างได้ เราพบว่าผู้เล่นมักจะพุ่งความสนใจไปในทิศทางที่กำลังเคลื่อนที่ ดังนั้นด้วยการใช้หน้าผา และให้ผู้เล่นปีนขึ้นไป เราแน่ใจว่าผู้เล่นจะต้องมองขึ้น และเตรียมพร้อมสำหรับศัตรู หากเส้นทางของผู้เล่นจะต้องเคลื่อนที่ผ่านด้านล่างของหน้าผา คงเป็นการยากที่เขาจะสังเกตว่าทหารกำลังโรยตัวลงมาจากด้านบน การตายจากการโจมตีที่มองไม่เห็นนับว่าไม่ยุติธรรมและไม่สนุกอย่างแน่นอน"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_cliffside.wav"		"[Robin Walker] The area you're currently entering is called the cliffside arena. We were particularly happy with the vertical cliffside in Half-Life 1, and regretted that we didn't iterate further on that concept in Half-Life 2. Vertical space allows us to force the player to deal with threats from above and below. We find that players focus their view on the direction they're travelling, so by using a cliffside, and having the player ascend it, we ensure the player will look up and be prepared for enemies. If the player's path was to move past the bottom of the cliffside, it would be unlikely he would notice the soldiers rappelling down from above. Dying from unknown threats never feels fair, and certainly isn't fun."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_courtyard.wav"		"[Robin Walker] ลานด้านหน้าของคุณเป็นพื้นที่ที่เราเรียกว่าอารีน่า อารีน่าถูกสร้างเพื่อถ่วงเวลาผู้เล่นไว้ระยะหนึ่ง และโดยปกติจะมีการต่อสู้ หรือความท้าทายอื่นๆ ส่วนใหญ่จะมีทางเข้าของศัตรูหลายทาง และมีประตูหรืออะไรบางอย่างที่ป้องกันไม่ให้ผู้เล่นไปต่อได้ จนกว่าจะจัดการอุปสรรคได้ ในกรณีนี้ อารีน่าจะไม่มีศัตรูจนกว่าผู้เล่นจะไขปริศนา และเปิดสัญญาณเตือน ด้วยวิธีการนี้ทำให้ผู้เล่นสามารถสำรวจอารีน่า และทำความรู้จักกับพื้นที่ก่อนทำการต่อสู้ ซึ่งจะเพิ่มความรู้สึกแปลกให้กับผู้เล่นที่คาดว่าจะถูกโจมตีทันทีที่มาถึงเป้าหมายที่กำหนดไว้ที่จุดเริ่มต้นของแผนที่ การหยุดการต่อสู้ที่นี่เป็นส่วนสำคัญของการไต่ระดับ เนื่องจากผู้เล่นสามารถรักษาอาการบาดเจ็บและสำรวจพื้นที่ได้เล็กน้อย หลังจากถูกโจมตีตลอดทางที่ปีนหน้าผา"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_courtyard.wav"		"[Robin Walker] The courtyard in front of you is a space we call an Arena. Arenas are built to hold the player for a period of time, and usually contain combat or some other challenge. They often have multiple entry-points for enemies, along with a gate of some kind to prevent the player moving on, until the challenge has been completed. In this case, the arena is free of enemies until the player solves a puzzle, and triggers an alarm. This is a method that allows the player to explore the arena, and get a sense of its space before being forced to fight in it. It adds a sense of uneasiness to the player, who's expecting to be attacked now that they've reached the goal set for them at the start of the map. The break in action here is also a crucial part of the level's pacing. It allows the player to recover and explore the world a little, after being attacked on the way up the cliffside."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_hdr.wav"		"[Gary McTaggart] ด้วยการเรนเดอร์แบบธรรมดาดังที่ปรากฏทางด้านซ้าย หากวัตถุบางอย่างบนจอภาพมีการสะท้อนแสง 20% เช่น ทรายเปียกๆ ความสว่างที่สะท้อนสูงสุดคือ 20% ของความสว่างสูงสุดของจอภาพคุณเท่านั้น การจำลองแสงที่ถูกต้องยิ่งขึ้นของ HDR ช่วยให้การสะท้อนของแสงอาทิตย์บนทรายเปียกๆ นี้ปรากฏอย่างที่ควรจะเป็นในโลกแห่งความจริง ซึ่งอาจใช้ความสว่างของจอภาพสูงสุด 100% HDR จะใช้ Bloom เพื่อจำลองแสงที่เกิน 100% ของความสว่างสูงสุดของจอภาพ"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_hdr.wav"		"[Gary McTaggart] With conventional rendering, seen here on the left, if something on the screen is 20% reflective, like the wet sand, then the maximum reflected brightness could only be 20% of the maximum brightness of your monitor. HDR's more accurate simulation of light ensures that the sun's reflection on this wet sand appears as it would in the real world, which could potentially use 100% of the maximum monitor brightness. HDR uses bloom to simulate light that is beyond 100% of a monitor's maximum brightness."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_intro.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] ยินดีต้อนรับสู่ Lost Coast ในการเที่ยวชมนี้ เราจะแนะนำเทคโนโลยีใหม่ด้านกราฟิกที่เราได้พัฒนาขึ้น นั่นคือ High Dynamic Range Lighting หรือ HDR และเราจะให้คุณได้ทราบถึงความท้าทายในด้านการออกแบบและการผลิตที่เราพบระหว่างการสร้าง Lost Coast อันดับแรก รายละเอียดโดยย่อสำหรับระบบคำอธิบายมีดังนี้ ในการฟังจุดที่มีคำอธิบาย ให้วางกรอบเล็งบนสัญลักษณ์คำอธิบายที่ปรากฏ และกดปุ่ม +USE ในการหยุดคำอธิบาย ให้วางกรอบเล็งบนจุดที่กำลังหมุนอยู่และกดปุ่ม +USE อีกครั้ง จุดที่มีคำอธิบายในบางตำแหน่งอาจทำการควบคุมเกมเพื่อแสดงอะไรบางอย่างให้คุณทราบ ในกรณีเหล่านี้ เพียงแค่กดปุ่ม +USE จะเป็นการหยุดคำอธิบาย"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_intro.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] Welcome to the Lost Coast. In this tour, we're going to be talking about a new graphics technology we've been developing, called High Dynamic Range Lighting, or HDR. We'll also be giving you some insight into the design and production challenges we faced during the construction of the Lost Coast. First, a quick explanation of the commentary system. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating commentary symbol and press the +USE key. To stop the commentary, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press your +USE key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game for the purpose of showing something to you. In these cases, simply pressing your +USE key will stop the commentary."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_intro_nohdr.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] ยินดีต้อนรับสู่ Lost Coast ในการเที่ยวชมนี้ เราจะแนะนำเทคโนโลยีใหม่ด้านกราฟิกที่เราได้พัฒนาขึ้น นั่นคือ High Dynamic Range Lighting หรือ HDR และเราจะให้คุณได้ทราบถึงความท้าทายในด้านการออกแบบและการผลิตที่เราพบระหว่างการสร้าง Lost Coast อันดับแรก รายละเอียดโดยย่อสำหรับระบบคำอธิบายมีดังนี้ ในการฟังจุดที่มีคำอธิบาย ให้วางกรอบเล็งบนสัญลักษณ์คำอธิบายที่ปรากฏ และกดปุ่ม +USE ในการหยุดคำอธิบาย ให้วางกรอบเล็งบนจุดที่กำลังหมุนอยู่และกดปุ่ม +USE อีกครั้ง จุดที่มีคำอธิบายในบางตำแหน่งอาจทำการควบคุมเกมเพื่อแสดงอะไรบางอย่างให้คุณทราบ ในกรณีเหล่านี้ เพียงแค่กดปุ่ม +USE จะเป็นการหยุดคำอธิบาย"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_intro_nohdr.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] Welcome to the Lost Coast. In this tour, we'll be talking about a new graphics technology we've been developing, called High Dynamic Range, or HDR for short. We'll also be giving you some insight into the design and production challenges we faced during the construction of the Lost Coast. It appears that you either have HDR disabled, or your video hardware does not support HDR. You're still welcome to take a look around the level. First, a quick explanation of the commentary system. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating lambda symbol and press your use key. To stop a commentary node, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press the use key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game for the purpose of showing something to you. In these cases, simply pressing your use key again will stop the commentary."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_monastery01.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] เราต้องการเปลี่ยนจากพื้นที่สว่างและเปิดโล่งไปสู่พื้นที่แคบและปิดทึบเพื่อแสดงไดนามิกโทนแมปปิ้งของ HDR และเราต้องการแสดงองค์ประกอบที่มีความตัดกันในฉากของเรา เช่น สถาปัตยกรรมของมนุษย์โบราณ และเทคโนโลยีของ Combine ที่ล้ำยุค วิหารสามารถตอบสนองความต้องการนี้ได้เป็นอย่างดี โดยทั่วไปวิหารมักจะตั้งอยู่โดดเดี่ยว ในที่มืด และถูกสร้างขึ้นเมื่อนานมาแล้ว ซึ่งจะเป็นฉากหลังที่วิเศษสำหรับเทคโนโลยีของ Combine ที่ขัดแยังกัน เมื่อเราสร้างฉากสมมติ เราพยายามเพิ่มความสมจริงโดยการอิงกับสถานที่ซึ่งมีอยู่จริง เราใช้สถานที่นี้เป็นข้อกำหนดในการออกแบบซึ่งทำให้เกิดความสอดคล้องกันอย่างลงตัวเบื้องหลังงานศิลป์"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_monastery01.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] We wanted to transition from a bright, wide-open space into a tighter, closed one to showcase HDR’s dynamic tonemapping. We also like to focus on contrasting elements in our settings, like ancient human architecture and futuristic combine technology. A monastery fit these requirements perfectly. Monastery's are generally isolated, unlit, and built ages ago. They provide a great backdrop for the contrasting combine technology. When we build fictional settings, we try to ground them by basing them off a real-world location. We use this location as a design constraint that forces a logical consistency behind the art choices."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_monastery02.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] โบสถ์เป็นสถานที่ที่น่าทึ่งอย่างมาก โดยปกติจะเป็นสถานที่ที่สว่าง แต่มีส่วนที่มืดที่สุดและสว่างที่สุด จึงเหมาะสมสำหรับการแสดง HDR โบสถ์แบบกอธิคซึ่งเป็นสถานที่ที่ดูเคร่งขึมและมีสีเดียวอย่างที่คุณเห็นในภาพยนตร์หรือเกมสยองขวัญส่วนใหญ่ ในทางกลับกัน โบสถ์ไบเซนไทน์จะมีสีสันหลากหลายและมีวัสดุหลายชนิด เราต้องการสีสันและวัสดุที่หลากหลายเพื่อแสดงการสะท้อนแสงของ HDR"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_monastery02.wav"		"[Viktor Antonov] Churches are great dramatic spaces. They’re often lit naturally, with extremes of darkness and brightness, which makes them a great showcase for HDR. Gothic churches are the sober, monochromatic spaces that you’ve seen in almost every horror movie or game. Byzantine churches, on the other hand, are very colourful and have a large variety of materials. We wanted that color & material variety to show off our HDR reflections."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_puzzle.wav"		"[Robin Walker] เกมของเราเต็มไปด้วยสิ่งที่เราเรียกว่า “ประตู” ซึ่งแท้จริงแล้วเป็นอุปสรรคที่ผู้เล่นจะต้องเอาชนะให้ได้เพื่อเล่นต่อไป เราใช้ปริศนาในที่นี้ เนื่องจากผู้เล่นเพิ่งผ่านการต่อสู้และการสำรวจพื้นที่ เมื่อเราออกแบบอุปสรรค เราพยายามทำให้ทั้งเป้าหมายของผู้เล่นและสิ่งที่ผู้เล่นต้องทำนั้นน่าสนุก เป็นเรื่องไม่ยากในการสร้างเป้าหมายที่น่าสนใจสำหรับผู้เล่น เช่น การหยุดเครื่องจักรนี้ไม่ให้ถล่มหมู่บ้านที่อยู่ใกล้ๆ แต่สิ่งที่ผู้เล่นจะต้องทำเพื่อเอาชนะอุปสรรคนี้จะต้องสนุกสนานด้วย แทนที่จะต้องทำสิ่งที่น่าเบื่อ เช่น การกดสวิตช์ปิด ผู้เล่นจะต้องใช้รหลักฟิสิกส์เพื่อทำให้กลไกของปืนติดขัดและใช้การไม่ได้"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_puzzle.wav"		"[Robin Walker] Our games are filled with things we call “gates”, which are essentially just challenges that the player must overcome to drive the experience forward. We used a puzzle here, since the player has been through combat and exploration recently. When we design challenges, we try to ensure that the player’s goal and the action required by the player are both fun. It’s not hard to create interesting goals for the player, like stopping this machine from shelling the nearby village. But the action required by the player to solve the challenge needs to be fun as well. So instead of something menial, such as hitting an off switch, the player gets to use physics to jam the gun’s mechanism and cause it to break."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_shader.wav"		"[Chris Green] เอ็นจิน Source รองรับเชดเดอร์ได้หลายแบบ เชดเดอร์การหักเหที่หน้าต่างตรงนี้ต้องการให้เราคัดลอกฉากเป็นเท็กซ์เจอร์ ทำการหักเห และนำไปใช้กับพื้นผิวหน้าต่าง เพื่อการสนับสนุน HDR อย่างเต็มที่ เชดเดอร์ทุกแบบในเอ็นจินจะต้องมีการอัปเดต ดังนั้นเชดเดอร์การหักเหนี้จึงได้รับการปรับปรุงเพื่อสนับสนุนทุกช่วงความเข้ม"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_shader.wav"		"[Chris Green] The Source engine supports a wide variety of shaders. The refraction shader on the window here requires us to copy the scene to a texture, refract it, and then apply it the window surface. To fully support HDR, every shader in the engine needed to be updated, so this refraction shader was improved to the support the full range of contrast."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_shipnode.wav"		"[Robin Walker] ซากของเรือที่อยู่ด้านหน้าคุณเคยเป็นส่วนหนึ่งของปริศนาที่เราตัดออกจาก Lost Coast การออกแบบดั้งเดิมของปริศนาคือแนวคิดที่ว่าผู้เล่นและชาวประมงได้ร่วมมือกันเพื่อแก้ปัญหาบางอย่าง นี่คือประเภทหนึ่งของปริศนาที่เราต้องการให้มีใน HL2 เสมอ แต่น่าเสียดาย ในขณะที่การพัฒนา Lost Coast ใกล้เสร็จแล้ว และปริศนานี้ยังไม่เสร็จ เราจึงตัดสินใจตัดออก การตัดงานที่ทำออกเป็นสิ่งเจ็บปวดเสมอ ดังนั้นเราจึงพยายามพัฒนากระบวนการตัดสินใจในลักษณะนี้ ตัวอย่างเช่น เราถามตัวเองเกี่ยวกับปริศนานี้ว่า 'ปริศนานี้สนุกจริงหรือ' 'ถ้าไม่สนุก ต้องทำงานเพิ่มแค่ไหนถึงจะทำให้สนุก' 'ปริศนานี้เหมาะสมกับวัตถุประสงค์ของ Lost Coast หรือไม่' 'ลูกค้าของเราจะพอใจกับปริศนาที่กำลังจะเสร็จนี้มากกว่าทหารที่กำลังโรยตัวจากหน้าผาหรือไม่' ขั้นสุดท้าย สิ่งที่เหมาะสมที่สุดคือวางปัญหานี้ไว้บนหิ้งกับไอเดียน่าสนใจอื่นๆ แล้วค่อยย้อนกลับมาใหม่"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_shipnode.wav"		"[Robin Walker] The remains of the ship in front of you were once part of a puzzle we cut out of the Lost Coast. The original design of the puzzle was based on the idea of the player and the fisherman co-operating together to solve something. This was a type of puzzle we’d always wanted to attempt in HL2. Unfortunately, as development on Lost Coast neared the end, and this puzzle still wasn’t finished, we decided to cut it. It’s always painful to remove work, so we’ve tried to evolve a process for making those kinds of decisions. For example, with this puzzle we asked ourselves 'Is this puzzle actually fun?', 'If not, how much work does it need to be fun?', 'Does this puzzle fit within the purpose of Lost Coast?', 'Would our customers appreciate this puzzle being finished more than they would appreciate, say, soldiers rappelling off the cliffside?'. In the end, it made the most sense to put this problem on the shelf with other interesting ideas, and come back to it later."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_tone.wav"		"[Chris Green] หนึ่งในคุณสมบัติของ HDR ของเราคือไดนามิกโทนแมปปิ้ง วิธีที่ง่ายที่สุดในการนึกถึงไดนามิกโทนแมปปิ้ง คือ เป็นวิธีในการจำลองลักษณะของแสงที่มีผลต่อตาของมนุษย์ ในความเป็นจริง คุณอาจเดินเข้าไปในห้องที่มืดและคุณสังเกตได้ว่าตาของคุณกำลังปรับเข้ากับความมืด ช่วยให้คุณมองเห็นได้ดีขึ้นเมื่อผ่านไปสักระยะ หรือคุณเดินออกมาสู่ที่สว่าง และแสงอาทิตย์ทำให้คุณมองไม่เห็น คุณเพียงให้ตาของคุณปรับและคุณจะมองเห็นตามปกติ ม่านตาของคุณจะปรับตามปริมาณของแสงที่เข้าสู่ตาของคุณ ไดนามิกโทนแมปปิ้งจะจำลองปรากฏการณ์นี้ โดยการปรับแสงในฉากเพื่อเลียนแบบการทำงานของม่านตาโดยอัตโนมัติ คุณจะเห็นเป็นภาพที่เคลื่อนที่จากอุโมงค์ที่มืดไปยังที่ที่มีแสงแดดจ้า และกลับไปอีกครั้ง ที่นี่คุณจะเห็นวิธีการที่เราคำนวณปริมาณแสงที่เข้าสู่ตาของผู้เล่น เราจะบันทึกฉาก และแยกระดับความสว่างเพื่อหาระดับแสงเฉลี่ย นอกจากนี้ เราจะให้ความสำคัญกับแสงที่จุดกึ่งกลางของจอภาพมากกว่าบริเวณขอบ เพื่อให้จำลองลักษณะของสายตาให้ดียิ่งขึ้น"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_tone.wav"		"[Chris Green] One of the features of our HDR solution is dynamic tonemapping. The easiest way to think about dynamic tonemapping is that it is a method of simulating the way the human eye reacts to light. In the real world, you’ve probably walked into a dark room and noticed your eye adjusting to the darkness, letting your see better after some time. Or you’ve walked out into a bright day, and been blinded by the sun, only to have your eye adjust and allow you to see normally. Your iris is adjusting itself in response to the amount of light hitting your eye. Dynamic tonemapping simulates this, by automatically adjusting the exposure of the scene to mimic the behavior of your iris. You can see this as the view moves from the dark tunnel to the bright sun, and back again. Here you can see the way we calculate the amount of light hitting the player’s eyes. We take a snapshot of the scene, and extract the brightness levels to get the average level of light. Additionally, we consider light at the center of the screen more important than that at the edges, to better simulate the geometry of the eye."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_water.wav"		"[Gary McTaggart] การเรนเดอร์น้ำเป็นความท้าทายอย่างมากสำหรับเรา ในความจริงแล้ว เราเรนเดอร์ภาพนั้น 3 ครั้ง หนึ่งครั้งสำหรับการหักเหของสิ่งที่อยู่ใต้น้ำ หนึ่งครั้งสำหรับการหักเหของสิ่งที่อยู่หนือน้ำ และอีกหนึ่งครั้งจากมุมมองของผู้เล่น คุณจะเห็นการสะท้อนและการหักเหของฉากในหน้าต่างเล็กๆ สองหน้าหน้าบนหน้าจอ ในการหักเห เราจะคำนวณปริมาณน้ำที่คุณกำลังมองเป็นพิกเซลเพื่อสร้างหมอกใต้น้ำตามปริมาณ และเพื่อจำลองอนุภาคขนาดเล็ก เพื่อการใช้งาน HDR อย่างเต็มรูปแบบ เราได้ตรวจดูเอ็นจินทั้งหมดและแก้ไขโค้ดทุกบิตที่คำนวณแสงและสี ตัวอย่างเช่น การเรนเดอร์การสะท้อนและหักเหของน้ำเหล่านี้ได้รับการปรับปรุงเพื่อสนับสนุนค่าความเข้มทุกระดับ"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_water.wav"		"[Gary McTaggart] Water presents us with a lot of rendering challenges. In fact, we have to render the scene 3 times. Once for the refraction of what’s under the water, once for the reflection of everything above the water, and once from the player’s view. You can see the reflection & refraction scenes in the two small windows onscreen. In the refraction, we calculate, per-pixel, how much water you’re looking through to do a volumetric underwater fog, to simulate particulate matter. For our full HDR solution, we had to go through the entire engine and modify every bit of code that calculated light and color. For example, these water reflection & refraction renderings had to be improved to support the full range of contrast values."
"#lostcoast\commentary\comm_outro.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] นี่คือจุดสุดท้ายของการเที่ยวชม Lost Coast นี่คือการทดลองของเราเพื่อดูว่ากลุ่มลูกค้ามีความสนใจในข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับกระบวนการพัฒนาของเราหรือไม่ เราใส่ใจในความคิดเห็นของคุณเสมอ คุณสามารถติดต่อเราได้ที่ gaben@valvesoftware.com หากมีคนชอบ เราจะสร้างเนื้อหาในลักษณะนี้ต่อไปสำหรับทุกเกมของเรา ขอบคุณครับที่ให้ความสนใจ"
"[english]#lostcoast\commentary\comm_outro.wav"		"[Gabe Newell] This marks the end of the Lost Coast tour. This has been an experiment on our part to see if our community would find it interesting to learn more about our development process. As always, we're interested your feedback. I can be reached at gaben@valvesoftware.com. If people like this, we’ll keep producing this kind of content for all of our games going forward. Thanks for listening!"
}
}
